All right.
In this lecture
we're going to talk about service meshes.
It's just a primer on service meshes.
What they are and their benefits
and whether you want to use them or not.
The idea here is that the complexity
of networking, which is really complex,
to be brutally honest,
I want to kind of get rid
of as much of that,
networking configurability,
and complexity
as I can by moving to a service
to service communication.
In doing this, services
now know about other services
instead of where they're actually running.
So it abstracts away
all that complexity and provides
traffic management,
security, observability without modifying
the application code at all,
which is actually pretty slick.
Again,
we're moving from more configurability
to more convention
by moving into a service mesh.
Okay.
So if I'm looking at, service mesh
architecture at the high level,
the service meshes use, concept
called a sidecar proxy on the sidecar.
Proxy sits inside the pod itself
and sits
right next to each individual container.
So this is different than a cube
kube proxy.
This is for the individual container
or the individual service.
Then that is running
all the communication actually
goes through these sidecars
and communicates sidecar to sidecar.
Now the benefits of
that is inside each sidecar
I've got connectivity
to a service registry,
a traffic management
certification authority and security.
So we baked all those key
elements security,
resilience, traffic management,
load balancing, scalability.
All is built into that control plane
that is running,
basically through the sidecar proxy.
So however, everything is managed
through that sidecar proxy.
The containers don't need to know
any of that stuff.
It's all handled for you.
So great concept.
Because of all the, I've got central,
control over over all my services.
This way.
And it
decreases the amount of complexity
on spreading that,
all those concepts across
all your containers.
Instead,
they're just contained in the sidecar.
So that's way to think of things is
I've got my data plane,
which are the sidecar proxies,
because they're handling all the traffic
and they're deployed
along with each application container.
So every container has one.
It intercepts
all the inbound and outbound traffic.
And through these proxy
examples of this are like envoy
or linker link or two, proxies.
I've got my control plane.
There's a centralized control component
that allows me to manage
and configure
the proxies that are in my data plane,
right.
Service discovery happens here.
Traffic policies,
mutual TLS certificates, security,
all that stuff happens in there.
Examples of this are it's your linker
D, control plane, things like that.
But I need both. Obviously.
The key features that
we see on this,
I've already mentioned load balancing
routing rules, which goes into security
RI ties in a retries and timeouts,
which is my resilience.
Right.
The routing rules also can be added with
security as well in my traffic. Mr..
Key features here on security
is a mutual TLS
and identity and authorization.
So mutual TLS, this is great
when I'm encrypting traffic
between different services.
That handles that for me.
Identity and authorization.
This gives me fine grained access
and control over service identities
and policies.
Which services could talk to,
which services, things like that.
Extremely important. So.
All right.
Let's talk about the observability
in these service.
Mesh architectures. Great.
Because everything's running to the proxy.
So I can see and control everything
that's talking between different,
services, different containers.
So I have metrics
I have distributed tracing,
I've got logging
all that's kind of built in.
So it's a it's
a great way to go for this architecture.
Not only the observability.
You also have resilience.
I can use a circuit, circuit
breaking to prevent cascading failures
or halting calls on unhealthy services.
I know a service is having a hard time.
I can slow things down.
I can control traffic flow.
I can circuit break it, stop things.
I can inject, faults in there to simulate
failures or delays
and test for resilience this way too.
So this really moves us up
to that application
layer where I'm abstracting away
a lot of the complexity.
The infrastructure under the covers.
All right.
Let's talk about how it all works.
So when we do deployment
we inject a sidecar proxy
into each service
pod in Kubernetes or container
or and remember the sidecar intercepts
all the traffic via iptables.
So all the traffic
that's coming into that pod
or for that individual container
all goes through the, sidecar proxy.
And then the sidecar proxy
is going to send the calls
into the container itself.
Right.
So the control plane
is going to distribute all the routing,
security and telemetry configurations
across all of these, sidecar proxies.
So I have consistency across the board.
Right.
On runtime operations,
the proxies are enforcing all the policies
that collecting telemetry
and affording requests on as needed.
There are lots of different service
meshes out there and different techniques.
Some are combining, and even getting rid
of some of the underlying
networking, paradigms that are out there
moving directly to service meshes.
We'll talk about those in another time.
But the popular ones that you'll see out
there are it's
CL, it uses Envoy Sidecars,
which is, which is pretty common
that we're seeing out there.
It's, you know,
really, well known out there.
It does have some issues, though,
when in all these service
meshes do, when it comes to connectivity,
they require, pretty consistent
connectivity.
Linker D is more lightweight.
It it's simpler to set up and it's you.
So you might want to look at that.
Console connect is from HashiCorp.
It does service discovery ACL and TLS,
they all they all have,
that secure layer that you want.
And then there's an open service mesh,
which is a project, built on envoy.
And it has kind of it has, integrations
directly into Azure Arc
S, which can be, really important.
So there's lots of opportunities out there
to learn
more about these architectures
and which one you want to use.
Okay.
When do you want to use a service mesh
instead of just, you know,
your vanilla way that you're doing things?
Here's some here's some great examples on
when when you want service
to service communication
with zero trust environments.
You know everything's totally encrypted
and I want to lock things down.
Make sure that I know who I'm talking to
on the other side and that I don't trust.
You know,
I'm not just saying stuff into the ether.
This is a good way to go because I can.
I can control the traffic,
pretty aggressively as I need to.
And that's the other thing.
If I need to control,
fine grained control of traffic,
I can I can absolutely do that.
Also, great telemetry
on who's talking to who and when they're
talking at the application layer,
instead of just at the network layer.
I'm just looking at everything going on.
And then also if I want to test for,
fault tolerance and things like the,
it gives me the ability to inject,
faults inside, the systems,
if I'm doing chaos engineering
or anything like that,
it gives me that that capability.
Okay.
As we had more
tools, we got to use some best practices.
Don't go all out crazy.
Let's start small first.
When you're when you're using
these new tools for the first time,
first enable like basic mutual
tools and metrics.
First, then adopt incrementally
new policies and gradually,
gradually increase to critical services
that you need.
I remember
you are adding another process there
that could get overwhelmed sidecar
proxies, the use of CPU and memory.
So you got to watch them.
You got to make sure
that they're not going crazy
or that they got some issues or some loop.
They can chew up all the resources
just on handling network,
calls and communication between services.
So be careful there.
Also, you want to separate your mesh
enabled and non mesh enabled workloads.
So you have some namespace isolation.
If you don't you can actually create holes
in your security in a big way.
And then automate your cert rotation.
Ensure you've got seamless mutual TLS.
Renewal.
So those
are some of the best practices out.
All right.
So why is service mesh.
You should be able
to answer these questions.
Robust traffic management handles
it really are strong.
Security's built in deep
observability service to service.
Observability
or service to multiple service.
It's the observability is off the charts
and then built in
resilience is already in there.
By decoupling the networking
from the application code, it means
I can focus more on the application code
and not on the networking.
Things that are the.